# Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

Department of Psychology, The Ohio State University

✓ rfarouni@gmail.com • ♦ http://rfarouni.github.io/

I am currently a doctoral candidate in quantitative psychology at the Ohio State University. My research is focused on latent variable modelling and its applications to behavioral, neuroimaging, and bioinformatics data. I hold a master's degree in mathematical statistics and I have a strong background in machine learning, multivariate statistics, and scientific computing. I am passionate about the open access movement in education, research, and academia and I am dedicated to rigorous science in the public interest.

## Education

### Academic Qualifications.

The Ohio State University

PhD in Quantitative Psychology Advisor: Professor Robert Cudeck

Dissertation Topic: 'Deep Latent Generative Models'

The Ohio State University Master of Science in Statistics [GPA 3.80/4]

The Ohio State University Ohio, USA Master's Degree in Quantitative Psychology 2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modelling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

### The Pennsylvania State University

Pennsylvania, USA Bachelor's Degree in Psychology with High Distinction [GPA 3.93/4]

Course Projects.

- o Multivariate Statistics (STAT 7560): 'Retinotopic Mapping of the Human Visual Cortex Using Independent Component Analysis'
- Advanced Computational Statistics (STAT 7730): 'Bayesian Analysis of Noisy Images Using Markov Random Fields'
- Statistical Consulting (STAT 6750): 'Modelling Categorical Perception of Speech Sounds using Beta Regression'

Ohio, USA

Ohio, USA

2012-2014

2011-2012

2015-Present

# **Experience**

## Internship..... The Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program (BMI SIP) Research Lab of Professor Ewy Mathé, The Ohio State University 2016 **Project**: Developing an R package and a Shiny app for the analysis of data generated from genome-wide chromatin accessibility assays such as ATAC-seq and DNase-seq with the goal of identifying regulatory elements involved in the cancer epigenetic landscape. Teaching Experience..... **Graduate Teaching Associate** Ohio, USA The Ohio State University 2013-present Teaching Assistant for Psychology 2220: Data Analysis in Psychology **Test Preparation Instructor** Moscow. Russia Instructor of the Graduate Management Admission Test (GMAT) 2009-2012 Teacher of English as a Foreign Language Moscow, Russia Teacher of General and Academic English 2001-2009 Journal Review Service..... **Psychometrika** Ad Hoc Reviewer 2015 **Psychological Methods** Ad Hoc Reviewer 2016 **Conference Presentations Joint Statistical Meetings** Seattle Poster Presentation 2015 Poster Title: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a

sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model

# **Awards and Fellowships**

0	Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award The Ohio State University	2015
0	The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship The Ohio State University	2015
	Project Proposal, 'Deceding the Divole of the Face Image from	

**Project Proposal**: 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'

#### The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2014

## University Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2012

## **Technical Skill Set**

#### Statistics and Machine Learning

- **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R*, *Python*, and *Julia* depending on computing goals.
- Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Tensorflow and MXNet.
- Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan; Familiar with Venture.

#### Computer Science

- **Cluster and High-Performance Computing:** Good knowledge of running neuroimaging and bioinformatics analysis pipelines on the Ohio Supercomputer (uses the Torque scheduling system). Basic familiarity with distributed cluster computing using the Spark platform.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

#### Domain Specific Software

- Neuroimaging Analysis Software: Nipype, PyMVPA, FreeSurfer, SPM, FSL, and Pycortex.
- **Bioinformatics Software:** Experienced in analysing functional genomics data using R's Bioconductor set of tools, Bowtie2, MACS2, SAMtools, and bedtools.

## **Publications and Software**

# Journal Papers.....

o Baskin, E., Farouni, R., and Mathe, E. (2016). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. Submitted.

## Software Development.....

o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. Github Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE.

#### **Personal Details**

- Country of Previous Residence: Russia (12 years)
- Marital Status: Married
- o Interests and Hobbies: Evolutionary Biology, World Cuisines, Experimental Music
- Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (limited)